It may come as no surprise to you that
one of the topics I find endlessly
fascinating is the concept of higher
dimensions of space and in particular
wondering what four-dimensional shapes
might look like. I've got a bunch of
videos on the topic and an entire book,
too.
But in talking about higher dimensions
on the internet, I've come to realize
that that phrase means a lot of
different things to different people.
I've been tagged in videos about
paranormal phenomena claiming that
something I've said in one of my videos
proves the existence of ghosts. But I've
never wanted to say anything more than
this is a fun geometry puzzle. Studying
higher dimensions is actually a legit
mathematical pursuit and honestly sounds
really awesome to do as a job. People
with such jobs might work at
universities doing research or in a
variety of industries. Dimensions pop up
in so many different fields including
neuroscience, AI, statistics,
cybersecurity, quantum mechanics,
topology, algebra, physics, cosmology,
and even dressmaking. So I spoke with
three people whose jobs involve higher
dimensions to find out how they use them
and what they think about some of the
stranger interpretations.
>> I'm Aidan Sims. I'm a mathematician who
works on I guess I would describe it as
quantum mathematics. So the way that
that operates is that when you're
modeling a quantum system, for every
variable that you have to model, you
need a different dimension. So if you're
modeling arbitrarily complex systems,
you need arbitrarily many dimensions.
And so I work on how you [music]
transform spaces of arbitrarily large
dimension, basically.
>> The thing that I do study are
four-dimensional spaces. As as you know
in mathematics, there's like a like a
sort of division between pure maths and
applied maths. And I'm in pure maths and
we just sort of study these objects and
shapes without necessarily thinking
about whether they exist or what they're
useful for and we're just sort of to us
it's sort of like a fun puzzle and we're
trying to figure out what could possibly
be the properties of shapes like this.
>> So in statistics we think of
high-dimensional data and we think of
the case where because we're able to
collect so much data about everything
around us nowadays that basically every
piece of information you collect is
basically a new dimension. So the idea
how you take very large dimensional data
we're collecting and sort of understand
what the sort of lower dimensional thing
is.
It's which truly underlying our data.
>> These three experts are all
mathematicians but in three very
different fields and I was surprised to
see just how different their use cases
for dimensions were across quantum
mechanics, not theory and statistics.
>> When you say spaces, are you talking
about like spatial dimensions like
forwards and backwards?
>> Yeah, so this is this is interesting. It
is like spatial dimensions forwards and
backwards but the spaces that I'm
talking about are not the space that we
see around us. So the space that we see
around us is arguably either
three-dimensional or four-dimensional
depending on whether you count time.
But the mathematical model that
describes quantum systems involves I
mean the spaces are a mathematical
construction
that models how the quantum mechanics
works.
>> Is the space you're describing now
what's known as Hilbert space?
>> That's exactly right. Yeah, so a Hilbert
space um
is uh is a higher well, it doesn't have
to be high-dimensional but it's a it's a
space of arbitrary dimension where
there's a notion of angle. So we can
still make sense of what things are at
right angles to each other. That's what
distinguishes a Hilbert space.
>> If someone's talking about Hilbert space
and using it mathematically,
is it useful at all to think of it
geometrically? Like I guess like asking
yourself what is this infinite
dimensional shape I'm working with? Does
that sort of come up?
>> It does, a lot, and it's quite
interesting um
because
what we a lot of the theory a lot of the
starting point of Hilbert spaces is
figuring out exactly which of the things
we picture when we think of three
dimensions
still work no matter how many dimensions
there are and which ones you have to be
careful about and and instead use the
formal mathematics to understand what's
going on. Yeah, so it is very helpful
even though the space
may have 20 or 100 or infinitely many
dimensions, it's useful to picture it
like three dimensions.
>> There's no way for you to draw a an
interesting sphere in three dimensions
without having it
hit itself, intersecting itself.
>> knot a sphere in three dimensions.
>> Exactly. And the co-dimension is very
important because 3 - 2 is 1, and that's
not enough, basically. But
4 - 2, well, that's 2. And so it turns
out that you can take a two-dimensional
sphere and knot it in four-dimensional
space. So that's the sort of thing um
that that I study.
>> So one one word I've heard that might
relate to what you're saying there is
the phrase dimensional reduction. What
on earth is that?
>> So it's the idea that we have a very
large amount of data, but again, we're
only interested in a very sort of small
subset of that. So you see, you may
have, for example, a very basic example,
you may have like our 3D world here, but
actually our data lies on the surface of
a piece of paper, and maybe you sort of
bend and sort of distort that paper in
sort of funny ways, but it still really
only lives in two dimensions even though
it's in a three-dimensional space.
Here we're sort of thinking on a much
larger scale, so we have uh million
dimensions,
but really our data lives in maybe 100
dimensions or maybe sort of much much
lower.
So reducing these very large things down
to just two or three dimensions where we
can have some sort of human intuitive
understanding is a is a big step.
>> So far, this was sounding pretty
theoretical, but behind some of this
research, were larger applications in
building technology or other
interdisciplinary projects. Some of
these ideas do leave the research paper
and impact the world we experience
daily.
>> So the idea is you have a bunch of
computers that are nodes and you sort of
draw sort of links between them if they
communicate or if they share
information. You have these sort of
rings and sort of patterns that appear
and it's when these sort of rings and
networks disappear, this can be evidence
of a cyberattack.
So maybe an intruder has come into your
system and suddenly he's pinging lots of
messages around all the computers he can
find and and that sort of breaks all the
other structure that you would see in
your network. So you're using these sort
of shapes to try to spot and when they
sort of appear and disappear as evidence
of something's either going
anomalously wrong in your network. So
these are the sort of ideas that we're
trying to use in sort of cybersecurity.
>> Say, let's take something topical. Say,
quantum computers, all right? So if I
want a quantum computer that has just
two bits.
Um
you know, so in a in a normal computer
that wouldn't be enough to do much, but
just as a starting point. So
in a quantum computer you have qubits
and they have two possible states. They
could be a zero or a they could be a one
and each of those states
has to be modeled by a different and
orthogonal dimension, like another
dimension in the underlying abstract
space. So even to model two qubits,
they've each got two dimensions, so
that's four dimensions. So just for the
most basic quantum computer, you already
need more dimensions than we can
picture.
>> Now, just because something might have
practical applications, doesn't mean
that it always has to. Maths doesn't
need to be motivated by commercial
applications and most mathematicians I
know are really motivated by the joy of
puzzle solving and the magic of
discovery.
>> One of the things I really love about
topology, and this is something I
learned a lot later, is that um
it brings mathematics into
concepts that I'd never really thought
of as mathematics before. And so, for
example, when I think of something like
knot theory, which I do study, it just
blows my mind that you can use
mathematics [music] to study if two
knots are different. As As a child, if
someone had told that to me, I would
just
would probably wouldn't even believe
them. You know, I study four-dimensional
spaces, so they're not that concrete.
But, [snorts] I study them using my
intuition, and I think about them very
geometrically, and
um
that appeals to me more than like I've
spent some amount of time, you know,
working with equations and inequalities
and so forth, and those things can be
very precise, and I like that aspect.
But, to be able to draw pictures and
just sort of, you know, my preferred
type of mathematics is when you like,
you know, move things around with your
bare hands. I do feel like my job is,
you know, I solve puzzles all day, and I
think having these very visual problems
really brings a sense of play into it in
some sense, where you really feel like,
you know, as a child, you moved blocks
around, and that's really what I'm
doing. They're 4D blocks.
But,
>> But, they're That's a good analogy.
Exactly.
>> To understand why the maths of higher
dimensions is relevant to so many
topics, it's useful to know that the
word dimension doesn't always refer to
space, and really any parameter can be
considered a dimension.
>> Actually, a friend of mine who makes her
own clothes, she had a very nice analogy
of this.
So, she was talking about if she has a
pattern for a dress she's making, it has
some number of measurements that you
have to make. And then, this is a set of
numbers that corresponds to, you know,
your dress or my dress or someone else's
dress. Like, that collection of data
or potential data, that forms some
dimensional space. So, maybe you have a
simple dress that has just four
measurements, or a really complicated
one that has 12. So, you know, that
really complicated dress, that's a point
in a 12-dimensional space, versus the
simple one is a point in a
four-dimensional space. Maybe another
example that's
I don't know, closer to mathematics in
some sense
would be to think about like a matrix.
Suppose you have a 2 by 2 matrix.
And so if I just think of a single
matrix, it has four numbers in it. Let's
say four real numbers. That's just a
single item.
But you could try to think about, well,
what are the other matrices that are
close to this one? And you can imagine,
all right, if I just keep all four of
them
more or less the same and just slightly
change each number by just a little bit,
that's like a matrix that's close to my
original one. But I have four different
coordinates that I get to change and I
get to change them
independently of each other, right? And
so if I now think about the set of 2 by
2 matrices, if I just think of it as a
set, that's like just thinking about
infinitely many discrete points that are
not necessarily arranged in any way.
What is it that makes something a space
rather than just a set? Well, to me as a
topologist, the thing that distinguishes
those two items, those two types of
objects is this notion of closeness.
So
I get to decide like, okay, two matrices
are close or they have distance,
whatever,
if all of the, you know, I could like
add up the differences between all of
the numbers or something or I could take
the square root of the
square root of the sums of the squares
or whatever notion of distance you might
like. And so that additional notion of
like um
closeness is what would make the set of
matrices, 2 by 2 matrices, into a space.
Okay. And then 2 by 2 matrices, that's
something that, you know, we've been
thinking about for a long time.
And that is in fact a four-dimensional
space.
Not one that you necessarily live in
unless you're a 2 by 2 matrix, I guess.
>> In my videos, I often talk about
specific shapes, like a tesseract, which
is a four-dimensional cube. And some of
you have commented and asked, "What's
the point of this?" Or wondered if it
has any use beyond being a mind teaser.
>> Has thinking about a tesseract or
understanding one ever been useful to
you?
>> Um okay, so yes. Uh I can think of a
specific instance where I was doing some
research and and a tesseract was exactly
something that I needed to be able to
describe. The research really had
nothing to do with shapes or geometry.
It was actually to do with
combinatorics. It was just trying to
count how many ways I could build a a
system of a certain type. Um but the
mental picture or the mental model that
helped me to do the counting was a
tesseract. So it was nice to know that
thinking about 4D
>> shapes can sometimes be mathematically
relevant. I also wanted to broach the
topic of the paranormal. I wondered if
these experts were ever troubled by the
way that people sometimes talk about
higher dimensions and the use of
mathematical vocabulary to support
spiritual claims.
>> I love the um the richness of language.
And I it's a feature of all languages
and particularly English that the same
word means different things in different
contexts all the time. And we use a word
because it it conveys the the right
sort of notion to us or something or you
know what I mean. So
I guess
I I think that mathematicians use the
word dimension in a very technical sense
and that's fine because that's what
we're doing with it. And for us it's it
really is just a a way of counting how
many different variables are independent
from each other a lot of the time. Um
and that's how that's the way that we're
using the word dimension. If you watch,
I don't know, Avengers, they they're
using the word dimension when they talk
about multiverses and different
dimensions in a completely different
sense. And I can see where it's a good
way to indicate that it's not something
that we can see, it's something
completely, you know, orthogonal to the
way that we,
you know, um experience the universe or
whatever. I I think it's just a matter
of like all English words it's being
used differently and that's fine. And I
yeah, I guess for a mathematician we
spend a lot of our time
giving very very precise mathematical
definitions to words that already exist
to help us to communicate to each other
effectively and efficiently. So I guess
I can't really object to other people
also taking a word and and giving it the
meaning that that that helps them to
think about what they're working on. So
yeah.
>> To me to me dimensions really do mean a
like a degree of freedom. As a pure
scientist we we aren't really thinking
about what these
notions
correspond to in the real world if
anything. The most general thing that I
could do
uh there's something there.
And then someone else could come and
think about all right, what this is
actually a good model for something
else. And then now because I've done
this background work your life is a
little bit easier because you can just
use what I've used what I figured out
for you
but then specialize it in your in your
own realm. And so right? Spacetime seems
like a four-dimensional thing that's
wonderful. Uh I'm not going to be
thinking about it. There's you know,
people may well think about the fourth
dimension as some sort of
spiritual other world breathing but
that's for me in the notion of like what
does it mean in the real world?
Um
that's all that I'm doing at all. Um
It's very interesting.
I not what I'm doing.
>> Yeah, I love their perspectives and I
feel like I did get a better sense for
how mathematicians really think about
the fourth dimension. Everyone I spoke
to had a confidence that comes with
thinking about these abstract ideas
every day. They weren't intimidated by
them and instead showed how embracing
the rather simple foundations can lead
to a lifelong curiosity.
>> You talked about in one of your videos
being able to take something out of a
safe. Like there's a safe and it's
locked in two dimensions, but if you're
a three-dimensional creature, you can
just pick it up out of the safe and and
somebody in the two-dimensional universe
couldn't see it. A lot of what we do is
really exactly what you did in that
video, where we say
well, let's just imagine that all of
these dimensions are really just two
dimensions. And then what could we do in
the third dimension? And we we're still
restricted to we can only picture three
dimensions as well. And really a lot of
being a mathematician is learning
what things you have to be careful about
that might not be quite the same when
you do that analogy and where you have
to just go to the formal mathematics
instead.
>> I I'm glad to know that my video yeah,
has some grounding in what what
mathematicians are thinking about as
well.
>> Thanks for watching this video and
thanks to my Patreon supporters for
making it possible. [music]
A special shout out to today's Patreon
cats of the day, Hermes and Apollo.